<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable and necessary warning concerning present dangers and duties from the commissioners of the Generall Assembly, unto all the members of this kirk.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18425956</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18425956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107606</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107606)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1643:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable and necessary warning concerning present dangers and duties from the commissioners of the Generall Assembly, unto all the members of this kirk.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: slightly faded, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107606:1"/>
            <p>A SEASONABLE and Neceſſary WARNING Concerning preſent DANGERS and DVTIES, From the COMMISSIONERS Of the GENERALL ASSEMBLY, Unto all the MEMBERS Of this <hi>KIRK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by EVAN TYLER, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:107606:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107606:2"/>
            <head>25. <hi>Iunii,</hi> 1650. <hi>Poſtmeridiem.</hi> A ſeaſonable and neceſſary VVarning concerning preſent dangers and duties, from the Commiſsioners of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly, unto all the Members of this Kirk.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the eminencie of the danger and the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of our duty did not conſtrain us, we had rather choſe to be ſilent then to emit any publick warning to the land within ſo few dayes of the meeting of the Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; but we ſhould not only run the hazard of juſt blame from them, but alſo be conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to guiltineſſe in our ſelves, if we did not in a time of ſo great ſtrait, give warning to the Lords people both of their danger, and of their dutie.</p>
            <p>The Inſolent and ſtrange actings of that prevailing party of Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> theſe yeares paſt, in reference to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Government, are ſo well knowne, and have been ſo often and fully laid open in the former Warnings, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, and Declarations of this Kirk, that we need not now take up much time in repreſenting the ſame. Albeit the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the advancing of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107606:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the work of Uniformity there, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Government was the great dutie that the Lord called that Land unto, and which all the people of God in theſe three Kingdoms did ingage themſelves in Covenant to endeavour to the utmoſt of their power; yet doth that work ſo much deſired and longed for by all the lovers of <hi>Sion</hi> in theſe Nations, and all that concerns Religion, lye in the duſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether forgotten and deſpiſed by thoſe men, and in ſtead of the beauty and order that ſhould be in the houſe of God, a vaſt toleration of many groſſe errors is allowed, whereby ſo many and ſo monſtrous blaſphemies and ſtrange opinions in Religion have been broached and are vented in <hi>England,</hi> as the like hath not been heard of almoſt in any generation. And though Monarchy and the Power of Parliaments was the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and long continued Government of that Kingdom, yet have thoſe men uſurped above the Parliament whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants they were, and by open violence driven away many, and impriſoned ſome of the Members thereof, and have not onely taken away the houſe of Lords and deſtroyed the late King, but alſo ſubverted Monarchy it ſelfe, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Foundations upſide down, and labour to wreath the voke of their oppreſsion upon the necks of our brethren in <hi>England,</hi> not only in regard of that which concerns their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and eſtates, but alſo in regard of that which concerns their ſoules and conſciences, whereof that Ingagement that is now preſſed in <hi>England</hi> is a preſent and publick teſtimony, being a ſore bondage under which many in that land now groane; whoſe caſe and ſufferings for the work of God we deſire, not onely to remember dayly before the Lord in our prayers and ſupplications, but in every thing to regard it as if it were our own, being confident that ſuch as love the truth, &amp; cleave to the Covenant in theſe Lands, ſhall obtain mercy of God to be faithfull in the midſt of temptations, and that the Lord
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107606:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>will not ſuffer them to be tempted above that they are able to bear, but will give unto them the iſſue with the tempation.</p>
            <p>This party after that they have acted ſuch things in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and alſo ſore afflicted and oppreſſed our brethren in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> now conceiveing that they cannot be eſtabliſhed, and that they cannot eat the fruit of their own devices without contradiction, as long as the Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſtands in their way, threaten us with a warre, by drawing their Forces Northward, and ſending them in ſmall parties towards the Border, that it may be the leſſe diſcerned what they intend to do: And if the Lord in his righteous and wiſe diſpenſation ſhall ſuffer them to invade this Land, as it is to be ſeared, that the Gangrene of their errours may take hold upon men of ignorant and unſtable mindes, who have not received the love of the truth; So may we, if they prevaile, look for confuſion and deſolation, and that the Pil ars both of Religion and Government ſhall be ruined and razed in this, as well as in our neighbour land. It doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt place concern all the Inhabitants in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to draw near to God, and to mourn for their own ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and for all the ignorance and prophanity and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding that is in the land, and to ſtudie to make peace with God in Jeſus Chriſt: The continuance and increaſe of many of thoſe ſinnes, for which formerly we ſeemed to have been humbled, doth doubtleſſe grieve the ſpirit of God, and may if they be not ſpeedily and ſincerely repented of, and forſaken, provoke him to give us over to the luſt of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; Our King, our Princes, our Nobles, our Paſtors, teachers, and people have ſinned; <hi>Let us therefore ſearch and try our wayes, and turn again to the Lord: Let us lift up our heats with our hands to God in the heavens, that he may ſpare and ſave his people, that they be not a prey to the enemie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, As the Parliament of this Kingdome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107606:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>have taken care for putting the land in a Poſture of Defence, ſo we hope that none ſhall be ſo negligent of their duty, and ſo inſenſible of their danger, as not to give chearfull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the lawfull commands of their ſuperiours in thoſe things that concern the ſecurity of Religion, and peace of the Kingdome, and that are neceſſary for the defence of the cauſe and of their native country; but that every man in his ſtation and calling will willingly and cheerfully acquit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the diligent and faithfull performance of all the duties that relate unto thoſe ends.</p>
            <p>It is far from our meaning that any who are tainted with Malignancie and Diſaffection to the work of God, ſhould be allowed or permitted to aſſociate or joyn themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by parties in Armes, much leſſe do we mean that we ſhould aſſociate and joyn with them, or that they ſhould be imployed or made uſe of, or countenanced or permitted to be in our Armies. The Lord hath ſo far cleared his mind both by his word and works againſt theſe things, that they are very blind who are not convinced herein; and we have made ſo ſolemn publick confeſsion of this ſin that relates unto Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, and ſo ſolemnly engaged our ſelves againſt the ſame, that they among us, who ſhould again hazard upon it, ſhould ſeem to be deſperately perverſe: It were not only to give great ground of encouragement to the Sectaries, before whom Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants have already ſo often fled and fallen, but to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the hearts, and weaken the hands of men of Integrity and godlineſſe, who could hardly expect a bleſsing in the fellowſhip of ſuch; nay, it were from the words of our own former Confeſsion and Ingagement unto duties, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim a judgment againſt the land, till it were conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed without remedy. Wee are therefore bold in the Lords name to warne the Honourable Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all whom it concerns in the land, that they may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107606:4"/>be farre from ſuch a thing, and that they may take care in their reſpective places and Stations, to purge Judicatories, and Committees of all ſcandalous and diſaffected men, and ſpeedily and effectually to goe about the removing and purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out from the Army all men of a ſcandalous converſation, and of queſtionable integrity and affection in the cauſe of God, and that they imploy none but ſuch as are of a blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe converſation, and of approven Integrity in the Lords work: It ſhall be a ſhame for any in this land, to be ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and unbeleeving, as becauſe of the ſcarceneſſe of men to make uſe of others, then ſuch as are thus qualified. The Lord hath not only ſpoken it in his word, and verified it in his works in the dayes of old, but hath let us ſee it with our own eyes, that it is all one with him to ſave with few or with many, and that a few, whom God will countenance, are more worth then many againſt whom he hath a controverſie.</p>
            <p>It needs not be matter of ſtumbling or terrour unto any, that the army of Sectaries go masked under a vale of ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holineſſe, and that their interpriſes and defignes have been ſo long and ſo often attended with ſucceſſe: Theſe who know them well, will acknowledge that many of them are looſe and diſſolute in their way, and though ſome of them walk more circumſpectlie, yet how can they be accounted truely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; Godly, who love to walk in the Immaginations of their own hearts, and in the light of their own fire, and in the ſparkes that they have kindled, corrupting the truth of God, approving errors in themſelves, and tolerating them in others; and who having power in their hands, labour only to eſtabliſh ſaftie for themſeves, altogether neglecting thoſe thinges that concerne the Honour of God, and the Kingdome of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt: If any of them have any thing of the ſeed of God in them, it cannot but be much blaſted with the wind of their own vaine inventions, and choaked and keept
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107606:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>down with the cares of their corruptions: Theſe who ſhall compare their proceedings with the word of God, and the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne League and Covenant, or look to the effects that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes thereupon either to Religion or government, or to the bodies or ſoules of men, ſhall finde that notwithſtanding of any pretext, their way is much to be deteſted and abhorred. Neither doth the Lord ſpare to execute judgement againſt ſeducers and corrupters of the truth, becauſe they ſeeme not to be ſubject to perſonall out-breakings in their lives; Is it not the ground of the great threatnings againſt Antichriſt, that he makes many drunk with the cup of his abhominations, which yet for moſt part are covered with a vail of externall devotions? And can the many antichriſts now in <hi>England</hi> eſchew to partake of his plagues, who in ſo great a meaſure partake of his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſſe of that partie proves not the goodnes of their cauſe, or that they ſhall proſper ſtill; The Lord who is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful in councel, and excellent in working hath been pleaſed to put the rod of his anger, and the ſtaff of his indignation in their hand, for executing of his wrath againſt malignants, becauſe of the enmity &amp; oppoſition of that generation unto the cauſe and people of God: But if they ſhal invade this land, and exalt themſelves againſt the Lords inheritance, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are in Covenant with him, For whoſe ſake the Lord did clothe them with power for a time, for taking vengeance upon his enemies, Then ſhall they ſtumble and fall, and be broken in pieces: Though the hoſt of <hi>Senachribe</hi> did prevaile againſt <hi>Samaria,</hi> yet did they fall in <hi>Judah,</hi> and he did return with ſhame and was ſlaine with the ſword in his own land. That partie hath as yet no cauſe to boaſt that God hath proſpered them in armes againſt the Covenant, or againſt a praying people ſtedfaſt in the Lords cauſe, following his way, and waiting upon him for help and ſucceſſe: All their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107606:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>have hitherto bin againſt Malignants; &amp; now the Lord having performed ſo much of his work againſt that generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who knowes but the Sectaries day may alſo be coming, and that when the ſtate of the queſtion ſhall be changed, God may turn his hand upon them, &amp; bring upon them the judgments of abroken Covenant, as he hath ever don to al that look that way.</p>
            <p>We deſire that not only others, but the Sectaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may conſider, that when <hi>England</hi> was very low, and well nigh brought under the feet of the popiſh, prelaticall and Malignant partie, That this Nation was then much ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited for their aſsiſtance and reliefe, and even by ſome of theſe who have ſince that time been verie active and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall for the partie which now prevails in that land: The Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> were then ſo compaſſionate of their brethrens condition, that they were willing to joyn in a League and Covenant with them, which both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes even many of thoſe who are now in the Army did ſolemnly ſwear and ſubſcribe: In proſecution of the ends thereof, this Kingdome did ſend into <hi>England</hi> a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble army, by whoſe aſsiſtance the power of the Malignant partie was broken and brought low, and the Parliament &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>England</hi> put in ſuch a condition, that they needed no more fear the ſtrength of their enemies. This league and Covenant which was the foundation of <hi>Englands</hi> and the Armies deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and ſaftie, the armie hath now forgotten and trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under foot, and walk in all their proceedings no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereto, then darkneſſe is unto light: Neither doth it ſatisfie them to do ſo in their own land, but they threaten us alſo with warre, for no other reaſon, but becauſe we cleave to our dutie in theſe things, to which <hi>England</hi> ſtands no leſſe obliged unto by Covenant before the Lord then we doe. We may confidently aſſert and profeſſe before the world that the Lords people in this land are not conſcious to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107606:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelves of any wrong done to that prevailing partie in <hi>England:</hi> The engagment in the year. 1648. was no leſſe abhorred, and teſtified againſt by the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and by theſe that are now in place and power in the State, and by all the godlie in the land, Then it was by that partie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; Which did ſo farre convince the Houſe of Commons That in their letter to the Generell Aſſemblie of this Kirk in the ſame yeare, They profeſſe that they are aſſured, that theſe Impions and unwarrantable actions cannot be done with the approbation and aſſent of the Religious and well affected people of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that they do underſtand, that there are very few amongſt theſe who were in the engagement againſt them that firſt engaged with them in the Covenant and cauſe, but ſuch as are profeſſed enemies to them, how ever they were then content to proceed therunto that they might be the better decieve the people of <hi>England,</hi> And that therefore they are unwilling to impute ſuch evils to this Nation in Generall: It is known how many ſervent prayers and ſupplications were powred out in this Land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord againſt that engagment, and wee think wee may without boaſting ſay, that thoſe prayers had as much influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the defeat thereof, as all the power of that armie: And ſince that time that engagement hath been publickly diſavowed, diſclaimed and repealed by the Parliament of this Kingdom. Neither hath that party any thing to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge us concerning Malignants, both Kirk and State having conſtantly followed, and being ſtill about their duties againſt them, without conniving at, or complying with them in their courſes. It is true that this Kingdom and Kirk have proteſted and teſtified againſt the proceedings of Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in reference to Religion and Government; Which we could not but do, unleſſe we had forgotten our duty, and the Chriſtian mutuall tyes that lie upon us, not onely as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107606:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſiſter Churches, but as Covenanted Churches, and ſo make our ſelves partakers of their ſins, and expoſed our ſelves to the hazard of their plagues. We in this Land being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſcious to our ſelves of nothing but dutie; If they ſhall invade us for following the ſame, Shall not GOD look upon it and avenge it?</p>
            <p>Whilſt we incite men to their duty in the defence of the Kingdom againſt invaſion, and encourage them in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the ſame, We deſire not to be miſtaken, or that any ſhould ſo far miſconſtrue our meaning, as though we did thereby intend to ſtir up unto, or approve of an invaſion of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or an engagement in war againſt the ſame. In relation to peace or war in theſe Nations, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but very much commend and approve the reſolutions of the Parliament of this Kingdom, expreſt in their Letter of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> to the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, and Inſtructions ſent therewith to their Commiſſioners 1649. and now again renewed in another Letter to the ſame Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, wherein they acknowledge their obligations, and declare their reſolutions to obſerve the rule of remonſtrating firſt the breaches of peace, of craving juſt reparations, of uſing all fair means, of giving a preceding warning of three moneths before any engagement in theſe Kingdoms in war, And do hold forth this way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedour in clearing each others, and dealing plainly, as agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, not onely to particular Treaties, and to the many Tyes, Bands, and Declarations paſt betwixt the Kingdoms, but alſo to the Law of GOD, and practiſe of His people in his word, and to the common law &amp; practiſe of heathen nations, much more Chriſtian Covenanted Kingdoms; And plainly profeſs their confidence, that the Covenanted GOD of theſe Kingdoms, who did take order with theſe of this Nation, who did unlawfully engage againſt <hi>England,</hi> in the year 1648.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107606:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>doth ſtill live and reign, and will being ſhame and ruine upon whatſoever partie in either of theſe Nations, that without a neceſſary cauſe and clear calling, and without obſervance of the aforeſaid rules and order ſhall offend, and invade the other Nation: In all which we do agree with them in our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and reſolutions, and conceive that the whole Land is bound to tread the ſame ſteps, and to walk according to the ſame rules.</p>
            <p>Albeit we be diligently to take heed of the danger that threatens from Sectaries, and faithfully to beſtir our ſelves in our places and ſtations in the uſe of all lawfull and neceſſary means for preventing of the ſame: Yet are we not to forget, but alſo with the ſame diligence and care to take heed of theſe dangers and ſnares that threaten the worke and people of GOD from Malignants. Malignancie though a very evill weed, yet is not pluckt up, but ſtill continues to be one of the raging ſins of this Land, it being the ſnare, wherewith looſe hearts, who cannot endure Chriſts yoke are moſt readily taken. Hence it is that there be ſtill many of that ſtamp in all the three king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, who drawing encouragements to themſelves, from the influence they have upon the Kings Counſells, and harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in their way, by the proceedings of Sectaries, do ſtill follow their former deſignes, and wait for their day, and would rejoyce in the ruine or halting of theſe, who adhere to the Covenant: And experience proves that many of theſe who have ſeemed to repent of, and abandon that way, yet do not really ſhake off that ſin, that hangs ſo faſt on, but upon new temptations fall again upon that ſame wickedneſſe, and prove worſe then of before; which may be a caution to us not ſuddenly to truſt them. We make no doubt, but that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants will by all means endeavour that there may be room left for them to undermine the work and people of GOD, and engage the Kingdom in a new war, upon terms of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107606:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſtructive to Religion and the Covenant.</p>
            <p>In reference to dangers upon the right hand and upon the left, beſides any dutie already repreſented to us: We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it incumbent to us, ſeriouſly to recommend the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing particulars to all the Land, eſpecially to theſe that are in truſt, either in Judicatories or Armies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt to watch and pray that in nothing they be deceived, or come ſhort of the duty, whereunto the Lord calls them in a time of ſo many temptations and great difficulties.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Every one would labour not only for the knowledge of the truth, but to have the power and love thereof engraven on their hearts, that they may from an inward principle of grace and ſpirituall life avoid erour, and all the ſnares which lead thereunto, and be incouraged to contend earneſtly for the Faith, which GOD hath been pleaſed to deliver to his Kirk in this Land.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not only is open Malignancie to be avoided, but men would watch that enmitie againſt the work and people of GOD, which ordinarily is the birth of jealouſie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content and of familiar converſing with ſuch as are diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to or lukewarm in the cauſe of GOD, ſteal not into their hearts, and gain not upon their affections by degrees; Experience almoſt of all backſliding times and perſons hath proven, that the fellowſhip of men of a diſaffected or luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm temper, blunts the edge of tenderneſſe and zeal, and ſteals away the heart, firſt from honeſt inſtruments, and then from the cauſe it ſelf: There have been and are ſtill ſome in the Land, who in a cunning way of inſinuation foment jealouſies, and act diviſions, whilſt they ſeem to be friends to the Cauſe, and by this means do more harm then others by open violence; Theſe we would mark and avoid them, that we may neither endanger our ſelves, nor give offence unto others, nor prejudice the Cauſe of GOD.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:107606:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
4. We would take diligent heed, that in nothing we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from the juſt and neceſſary deſires of this Kirk and Kingdom, propounded to his Majeſty for ſecuring of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and ſetling the peace of the Kingdom; But that we cleave cloſely to our former reſolutions in thoſe things: If we remit and grow ſlack, and yeeld in any of them, as it ſhall increaſe the hopes and endeavours of carnall and diſaffected men, ſo ſhall it provoke GOD againſt us to leave us to our ſelves, till we be plunged in a pit of backſliding.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It concerns us to take heed that we do not tread the ſteps of thoſe, who carried on the late unlawfull engagement againſt the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> in any thing already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by this Kirk and Kingdom, eſpecially to beware of changing the ſtate of our Cauſe, or altering the matter of our qua rell, either by laying aſide of GODS intereſt and tak ng up of mans, or by preferring or equalling mans inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt unto GODS: This were to turn upſide down the whole tenour of our Principles and procedors, and not only to ſpoyl us of all the comfort we can look for from our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but alſo to bring upon our ſelves the guilt and reproach of all the ſin of thoſe, who carried on that engagement, ſo much condemned and born teſtimony againſt in this Land.</p>
            <p n="6">6. We would beware of loſing the advantage of defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſeeing our ſtrength moſt conſiſts in the equity and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Cauſe, and the holy and righteous way in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing of the ſame: It ſhall be better for us, rather to endure ſtraits for a time, then by precipitating and making haſt in the dark, to ruſh againſt the wall, and ſpoil our ſelves of that peace and comfort, which we may have in waiting till GOD go before us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We deſire that all the Land may be ſtill pouring out their prayers and ſupplications before GOD, that the Kings Majeſty may really and wholy abandon all Malignant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107606:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>principles and Counſells, and joyn cordially in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Cauſe of GOD.</p>
            <p n="8">8. As all the people of GOD throughout the Land would be carefull to diſcern of dangers and avoid ſnares from, and compliances with both Sectaries and Malignants, ſo would Miniſters be diligent and faithfull in preſsing of theſe duties, and that in a ſolide and convincing way, and labour to make it appear that they ſpeak not againſt the one or the other from paſſion or intereſt, but upon the grounds of divine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and from the light and authority of GODS Word, that ſo they may make themſelves manifeſt to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of their hearers, and ſtop the mouths of gainſayers.</p>
            <p>Finally all the inhabitants of the Land would be aware of pride and carnall confidence, and in a humble way would wait upon the LORD, and tread the ſteps of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, and he who hath done great things for us, ſhall yet ſave us.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. KER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
